<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on Alan Abbott</title>
        <link>/posts/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on Alan Abbott</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>Home Network Project</title>
            <link>/posts/2022/08/home-network-project/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>/posts/2022/08/home-network-project/</guid>
            <description>I recently moved into a new apartment and decided I needed to upgrade my home network. I still had a router that I got in college but I knew the technology had moved forward since then. I was also frustrated by my previous roommate’s wifi situation. I had dead spots in my room that made streaming difficult and I heard about it frequently.
We also qualify for fiber internet at the new apartment, and I could get near gigabit speeds for $55/month through RCN.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently moved into a new apartment and decided I needed to upgrade my home network. I still had a router that I got in college but I knew the technology had moved forward since then. I was also frustrated by my previous roommate’s wifi situation. I had dead spots in my room that made streaming difficult and I heard about it frequently.</p>
<p>We also qualify for fiber internet at the new apartment, and I could get near gigabit speeds for $55/month through RCN. I wanted to be able get that internet speed and come close to taking advantage of it on my network. Therefore, my requirements became a gigabit ethernet network for the home, plus wifi that is as reasonably fast as possible with good coverage of the whole apartment, including the back patio.</p>
<p>I also wanted to be able to VLAN segment my network and have separate wifi networks or SSIDs for each VLAN. I wanted to keep my smart devices from communicating with my personal devices, unless they needed to to perform a smart function. This requirement basically bumped me into small business / prosumer hardware, unfortunately.</p>
<p>I started looking at wifi, because this is really the only place I knew to look. I quickly decided I needed a Wifi 6 router, the latest and greatest protocol for the fastest speeds and most clients. Functionally this meant faster connection to my laptop and phone, since I was planning to hardwire the TV for streaming. The next questions were mesh or not? And do I want a separate router and access point (AP)?</p>
<p>I initially decided not to go for a mesh system, instead going for the cheapest Wifi 6 router I could find, this ASUS router. I planned to put it in AP mode and use a separate router for my VLANs and other traffic routing. This was a great plan until I realized you needed multi-SSID and VLAN support in the AP in order to have wifi devices on different networks. This meant to keep my light bulbs from hacking into my laptop, I needed an AP with VLAN and multi-SSID support. This directed me to the Orbi Pro Mini Wifi 6. This router was on sale I think at Micro Center because it had all the features I wanted, plus a mesh satellite, for only $40 more than the cheap ASUS. So this got me my AP for the network.</p>
<p>Next was the router / switches. I had decided in deciding my wifi AP that I would use a separate gigabit router for my network. This was motivated by getting a cheap Wifi 6 router and getting the rest of the required features from the router. When I upgraded to the Orbi, I didn’t reconsider my router choice. My system is working well for me, but I think I could maybe have used the Orbi for everything and skipped the separate router. Anyway. My router handles the most of the work for the network, and the Orbi APs give me multiple SSIDs to keep my devices separate.</p>
<p>I also used CAT6 cabling for all the runs between devices the the router. This lets me get gigabit speeds, fully capable of taking advantage of my fiber internet, anywhere with an ethernet cable. Currently I have a direct line to my home server, the Apple TV, and one under the couch for working in front of the TV. I also have my docking station hardwired in. This keeps me covered with fast internet most of the time, and the wifi is good and speedy everywhere else as well.</p>
<p>Overall probably not necessary, but it was a good learning exercise in setting up and managing a network. I also setup a Pi-hole DNS service so I am doing some basic ad-blocking and tracking prevention at a network level, but I’ll write about that later. It’s nice having fast internet all over the house. My nerdy inner child is so happy.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>New Garden!</title>
            <link>/posts/2022/08/new-garden/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>/posts/2022/08/new-garden/</guid>
            <description>My fiancé and I recently moved into a place with a good sized outdoor space, at least for Chicago. I decided to use the space to plant a vegetable garden, set up a grill and lights and hang my hammock. I was pretty overwhelmed at first, I had gardened with my dad before but that was years ago and I wasn’t taking thoughtful notes about the whole process. As a result I felt like I was starting from zero but luckily I was able to put together and revise a plan pretty quickly.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My fiancé and I recently moved into a place with a good sized outdoor space, at least for Chicago. I decided to use the space to plant a vegetable garden, set up a grill and lights and hang my hammock. I was pretty overwhelmed at first, I had gardened with my dad before but that was years ago and I wasn’t taking thoughtful notes about the whole process. As a result I felt like I was starting from zero but luckily I was able to put together and revise a plan pretty quickly.</p>
<h2 id="plan-a---hydroponic-dutch-buckets">Plan A - Hydroponic Dutch Buckets</h2>
<p>Initially I wanted to try out hydroponic gardening. Essentially hydroponic gardening is growing plants without soil, using some other media to hold water and nutrients near the roots of the plants. This can help conserve space, get more nutrients to plants, and allow for growing in places or configurations that wouldn’t be possible with soil.</p>
<p>The simplest (active) hydroponic garden, in my opinion, is a basic dutch bucket system. This consists of a 5-gallon or similar sized bucket, some means of getting water in the top, and a drain near the bottom. Ideally the drain should be 2-3 inches above the bottom of the bucket to allow some water to collect. The soil is commonly replaced with materials like perlite or coco coil. The water is treated with soluble fertilizers to create a nutrient solution. The nutrient solution and be collected and reused or drained to waste. This system is simple because it just involves getting the nutrient solution pumped into the top of the bucket and gravity to collect and reuse the nutrient solution.</p>
<p>Note: There are actually more simple, passive hydroponic systems, but these didn’t scratch the itch of building something enough for me, I had to go more complex.</p>
<p>After reviewing various setups, I decided several dutch buckets would be the way to go. I’d use 5-gallon buckets for the pots, PVC pipe for the drains and collection, a 55-gallon drum for the water reservoir, and a pump + host + dripper irrigation fittings to do the circulation.</p>
<p>I was able to source the 55-gallon drum from Facebook marketplace for $10. I was surprised by how many were listed for free/cheap, they seemed easy enough to find! I found some free scrap wood on Craigslist for street pickup. Initially I planned to get the lumber new but after seeing the prices I opted for a more economical and eco-friendly solution.</p>
<p>I found a fountain pump at Harbor Freight that met my height and flow rate needs. Pumps are typically rated for a certain height relative to the pump AT a certain flow rate. As the pump lifts water higher relative to itself, the flow rate will slow and eventually stop. Be sure that the pump you choose will give you the flow you need and the height you want.</p>
<p>Note: Flow rate is important to consider for some systems like Nutrient Film Technique (NFT) channels, but not for others that don’t run continuously, like flood-and-drain systems.</p>
<p>I planned to construct a short platform to set the buckets on and bury the 55-gallon drum deep enough to allow the solution to drain back into the reservoir. However, I never made it to construction because I was confronted by Plan B.</p>
<h2 id="plan-b---just-use-the-dirt">Plan B - Just use the dirt</h2>
<p>After explaining all the benefits of hydroponic gardens and why I wanted to try it, my fiancé made the fair point that it’s rare to have a patch of dirt in Chicago, so why cover the dirt with plastic buckets. This was ultimately the way we decided to go. The point that swayed me was she said she would spend more time outside with me if there was a nice garden. So, dirt garden it was.</p>
<p>I realize I don’t know much about gardening, so I venture to the local library. I haven’t been in a library in so long, it felt nice to feel like a kid in a candy store with books again. I find a few books on local plants and gardening and get checked out. After getting home and reviewing the gardening books. I decided to try and identify what plants I had in the garden and what condition the soil was in.</p>
<p>I used the app iNaturalist to take photos of the plants in the garden and it suggested classifications for them. It was helpful when other locals would comment and confirm or refine one of the AI’s suggestions. I used a few soil tests from the books to assess the dirt. I would grab a fistful of dirt and squeeze and judge it based on how it crumbled as I let go.</p>
<p>After some consideration I decided that mostly the garden was full of weeds and local grasses and the dirt was in okay, but not great condition. I decided I needed to weed the garden and turn the dirt over to get ready for any new plants. This is where the fun and hard work began. I cleared the top layer of dirt and weeds, along with lots of trash and rocks from previous tenants. I also loosened the dirt to get ready for additional soil.</p>
<p>I thought the soil needed more sand, since it seemed to cling together a little too well. I decided to go with some of the cheapest stuff from Lowe’s that still had any nutrient content. I got 10 bags, hopefully enough to add a couple inches across the area I wanted to plant. I got the bags of dirt home and worked them into the existing soil. This was by far the hardest work but also the most enjoyable.</p>
<p>Once I had got the garden ready, we made a trip to a local nursery to get some plants for the space. We went to the Urhausen Greenhouses and found all the plants we could want. We got several varieties of peppers and tomatoes, as well as some cucumber and watermelon, and some Salvia and Marigold flowers. I planted them when we got home, gave everything a good water and have hoped for the best!</p>
<h3 id="plan-b---a-bonus-nft-system">Plan B+ - A bonus NFT system</h3>
<p>I also had all this free wood and PVC so I decided to construct a four channel NFT setup in the back of the dirt patch. This area doesn’t get a ton of sun anyway so it seemed like a decent gamble on the space. I used the wood to build A-frame supports for the PVC channels and screwed them in place. I buried the 55-gallon drum to be the reservoir and the channels will drain back into the drum. It’s a simple enough setup and hopefully will grow several small plants.</p>
<p>Overall it seems to be growing well and it has made the back space a much more enjoyable place to hang out! We’ve eaten several meals out here and I’ve started hammocking over the plants. I also enjoy fast wi-fi while doing this because of my overkill home network setup, which I will write about soon.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
