<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Alan Abbott</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Alan Abbott</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2024 18:28:45 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Home Network Project</title>
      <link>/posts/2022/08/home-network-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2022/08/home-network-project/</guid>
      <description>I recently moved into a new apartment and decided I needed to upgrade my home network. I still had a router that I got in college but I knew the technology had moved forward since then. I was also frustrated by my previous roommate’s wifi situation. I had dead spots in my room that made streaming difficult and I heard about it frequently.
We also qualify for fiber internet at the new apartment, and I could get near gigabit speeds for $55/month through RCN.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Garden!</title>
      <link>/posts/2022/08/new-garden/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2022/08/new-garden/</guid>
      <description>My fiancé and I recently moved into a place with a good sized outdoor space, at least for Chicago. I decided to use the space to plant a vegetable garden, set up a grill and lights and hang my hammock. I was pretty overwhelmed at first, I had gardened with my dad before but that was years ago and I wasn’t taking thoughtful notes about the whole process. As a result I felt like I was starting from zero but luckily I was able to put together and revise a plan pretty quickly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SSL/TLS Guide Part Three: Tools for Working with Certificates</title>
      <link>/posts/2024/06/ssl/tls-guide-part-three-tools-for-working-with-certificates/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2024 18:28:45 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2024/06/ssl/tls-guide-part-three-tools-for-working-with-certificates/</guid>
      <description>Contents Part One: Public/Private Keys Part Two: Certificates Part Three: Tools for Working with Certificates Windows and Java File Types
Windows and Java platforms utilize different file formats to store and manage TLS certificates. Understanding these file types is essential for proper certificate handling, installation, and configuration in various applications and systems. The following are some common file formats used for TLS certificates on Windows and Java platforms:
Personal Information Exchange (PFX) or PKCS#12: Windows systems often use the .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SSL/TLS Guide Part Two: Certificates</title>
      <link>/posts/2024/06/ssl/tls-guide-part-two-certificates/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2024 18:26:30 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2024/06/ssl/tls-guide-part-two-certificates/</guid>
      <description>In Part One we discussed public key infrastructure (PKI) and how it enables privacy and integrity of communications between two parties. However, we still have the issue of trust, and deciding whether to trust the holder of a given private key or not. In Part Two of my TLS guide we will see how X.509 certificates enable us to rely on central sources of trust to weed out bad actors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SSL/TLS Guide Part One: Public/Private Keys</title>
      <link>/posts/2024/06/ssl/tls-guide-part-one-public/private-keys/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2024 18:26:20 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2024/06/ssl/tls-guide-part-one-public/private-keys/</guid>
      <description>Transport Layer Security (TLS) or Secure Sockets Layer (SSL) protocols are the primary method for securing communications between servers and clients on the internet or other networks such as a plant floor or enterprise network. TLS is the successor to SSL, however the terms are used interchangeably, both referring to the newer TLS protocol. Without using TLS to encrypt the communication between servers and clients, their communications could be exposed to 3rd parties intercepting and possibly spoofing messages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Consulting</title>
      <link>/consulting/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2024 21:51:58 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/consulting/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kryptonite R-30 Rear Light Mount</title>
      <link>/designs/bike-rear-light-mount/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/designs/bike-rear-light-mount/</guid>
      <description>Replacement mount for the Kryptonite R-30 rear bike light.
This was one of my first attempts at using 3D design and FDM printing to create something functional for myself. I thought I had lost the light when I was cleaning up my bike for the spring and decide to toss the mount. As luck would have it I did not lose the light, and found it to be still very functional and bright.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kryptonite U-Lock Lock Mount</title>
      <link>/designs/bike-lock-mount/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/designs/bike-lock-mount/</guid>
      <description>A mount to hold your U-Lock to your bike!
This is the result of several iterations and proved to be a great learning experience. From the first version shattering as soon as I hit a curb to the current version tipping over when printing due to no supports, it was a really fun and useful way to learn more about 3D design and FDM printing.
This design can be found for free on Thangs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>Hi! My name is Alan.
I would describe myself as a builder, adventurer, someone who is constantly curious and wanting to learn more. I&amp;rsquo;m rarely satisfied with sitting still, not asking questions, or being told something isn&amp;rsquo;t possible. I like a good challenge and I&amp;rsquo;m constantly fascinated by the world around me.
I have been working with computers for nearly as long as I can remember, initially taking them apart and sometimes putting them back together.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
